<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo Academic CV Theme</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Hugo Academic CV Theme</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu7729264130191091259.png</url>
      <title>Hugo Academic CV Theme</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hugo personal</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/hugo-personal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/hugo-personal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My personal site for science. All infomation about me and my projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of bibliography</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 18:01:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-a-bibliography&#34;&gt;What is a bibliography?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bibliography is a systematic listing of sources used in a scholarly or research paper. It serves as an important tool for academic integrity and allows readers to verify sources of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;basic-elements-of-a-bibliography&#34;&gt;Basic elements of a bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;record-structure&#34;&gt;Record Structure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each bibliographic record should contain the full output data of the source: author, title, year of publication, publisher, and other relevant information depending on the type of publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;design-styles&#34;&gt;Design styles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different styles of bibliographic citations (APA, MLA, Chicago, GOST), each of which has its own peculiarities and is applied depending on the discipline and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;composition-principles&#34;&gt;Composition principles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;completeness-of-information&#34;&gt;Completeness of information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All sources referenced in the text should be included in the bibliography. Each entry should contain sufficient information to identify and locate the source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;uniformity-of-layout&#34;&gt;Uniformity of layout&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All entries in the bibliographic list should be organized in a uniform style, with the same rules of punctuation, order of elements, and formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;modern-tools&#34;&gt;Modern tools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bibliography-managers&#34;&gt;Bibliography managers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specialized programs (Zotero, Mendeley, EndNote) greatly simplify the process of creating and formatting bibliographic references, automating many routine operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;online-services&#34;&gt;Online services&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many scientific search engines and databases offer the ability to automatically export bibliographic records in a variety of formats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-importance-of-proper-design&#34;&gt;The importance of proper design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A well-designed bibliography not only demonstrates the depth of the research, but also allows other researchers to continue working in the field, ensuring continuity of scientific knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future-of-bibliographic-systems&#34;&gt;The Future of Bibliographic Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As digital technology advances, new formats for presenting bibliographic information are emerging, but the basic principles of academic integrity and citation standards remain unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The post for the week of March 24-30</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 14:41:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;start-of-the-week&#34;&gt;Start of the week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The week started off with great weather, every morning I went out for a run, exercising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;university&#34;&gt;University&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally started learning German, passed all my debts, wrote all my labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-a-game&#34;&gt;Making a game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continued writing the game, added a new chapter of the storyline, it took me the whole week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;poetry&#34;&gt;Poetry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first poem was very well liked and I posted it on the writers site, wrote 2 more poems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;website&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got an order for a website, it was pretty simple, I did it in 3 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a very productive week, got a lot done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The post for the week of March 17-23</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 23:06:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;start-of-the-week&#34;&gt;Start of the week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The week started off with a huge amount of rain and cold, my mood was at zero. By the middle of the week it started to get warmer and sunnier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sports&#34;&gt;Sports&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally found time to do some sports, went to the tourniquets, played table tennis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;test-and-other-studies&#34;&gt;Test and other studies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wrote a test on mathematical analysis for the maximum score, not in vain. I defended several programming labs and passed all my debts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-a-game&#34;&gt;Creating a game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued writing the game, but stopped on drawing sprites for characters, thought over the further plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;poetry&#34;&gt;Poetry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tried to write my first poem, it turned out pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a good week, it&amp;rsquo;s a shame I didn&amp;rsquo;t get out this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Markdown markup language</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 18:01:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-markdown&#34;&gt;What is Markdown?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown is a lightweight markup language that allows you to format text using simple characters. Its main advantage is readability both in its original form and after conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;main-features&#34;&gt;Main features&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headings&#34;&gt;Headings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown supports six levels of headings, allowing you to create a clear structure for your document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;text-formatting&#34;&gt;Text Formatting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use simple characters to italicize or bold text, create strikethrough text and monospaced text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lists&#34;&gt;Lists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language offers a convenient syntax for creating both numbered and bulleted lists, including multi-level nesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;links-and-images&#34;&gt;Links and Images&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert hyperlinks and images in an intuitive way without compromising the readability of the source text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;code-and-citations&#34;&gt;Code and Citations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For technical documentation, the ability to insert code blocks and citations is particularly useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;benefits-of-markdown&#34;&gt;Benefits of Markdown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main strength of Markdown is its versatility. Documents display equally well in any text editor and on all modern platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;applications-in-modern-development&#34;&gt;Applications in modern development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today Markdown has become the standard for project documentation, technical blogging, and content creation for static site generators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-of-the-language&#34;&gt;Future of the language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the emergence of alternatives, Markdown continues to evolve, retaining its original simplicity and elegance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Git version control system</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 23:06:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-to-version-control&#34;&gt;Introduction to Version Control&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In modern software development, Version Control System (VCS) is a must-have toolkit. Among distributed VCSs, Git, developed by Linus Torvalds in 2005, holds a special place. Its architecture is based on a directed acyclic graph (DAG) of commits, which provides efficient change history management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;theoretical-foundations-of-git&#34;&gt;Theoretical Foundations of Git&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-storage-model&#34;&gt;Data Storage Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git implements the concept of file system snapshots. Unlike delta-based systems that store differences between versions, Git stores the full state of files at each commit, using the SHA-1 hashing mechanism to identify objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;branching-mechanism&#34;&gt;Branching Mechanism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Branching in Git is the creation of a movable pointer to a specific commit. This implementation is highly efficient because it does not require duplicate files. Merging is accomplished through a three-way algorithm that takes into account the common ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;practical-application-considerations&#34;&gt;Practical Application Considerations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;distributed-architecture&#34;&gt;Distributed Architecture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each Git repository contains a complete history of changes, which provides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autonomous operation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increased fault tolerance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible collaboration between developers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;change-management&#34;&gt;Change Management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work process includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change indexing (staging area)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Committing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verifying history (log analysis)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Synchronization with remote repositories (push/pull)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;benchmarking&#34;&gt;Benchmarking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git shows advantages over centralized systems (SVN, CVS):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locality of operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impossibility of history loss&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for non-linear development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficient use of disk space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning Git is of significant value to future software development professionals. Its theoretical foundations illustrate advanced change management approaches, and its practical implementation sets a new standard for VCS. Further research could focus on analyzing conflict resolution algorithms and optimizing large repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The post for the week of March 10-16</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 23:06:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-school-week&#34;&gt;New school week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The week started off pretty hard, there were a lot of assignments that needed to be done, but luckily I got everything done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;game-development&#34;&gt;Game Development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my free time I worked on my game on Unity. I added sound and visual effects for the character, drew new sprites for other objects in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparing-for-a-test-paper&#34;&gt;Preparing for a test paper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepared for a test paper on matnematic analysis, it was quite easy, the topic was easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;weekend&#34;&gt;Weekend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished my week with a Sunday trip to the movie theater, the movie was pretty boring, but it was fun and interesting to watch even in the company of friends.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/experience/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post for the week of March 31 through April 6</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;start-of-the-week&#34;&gt;Start of the week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again the week started off with great weather, every morning I went out for a run, exercising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;university&#34;&gt;University&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studying German is well underway, I started learning Angular framework and I&amp;rsquo;m still learning TypeScript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-a-game&#34;&gt;Making a game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spent half of the week testing a new game, found a few bugs that I haven&amp;rsquo;t managed to fix yet. I drew a few more new objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;poetry&#34;&gt;Poetry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wrote a couple more poems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;website&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No orders for websites yet, but I started writing one myself to test Angular and TypeScript. It turned out pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a pretty boring week, but I met up with some friends over the weekend and had more fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific programming languages</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-scientific-programming&#34;&gt;What is scientific programming?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific programming is a specialized area of development focused on solving complex computational problems in various disciplines: from physics and mathematics to biology and economics. These languages are designed to work efficiently with numerical methods, statistics, and large amounts of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;main-representatives&#34;&gt;Main representatives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;python&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard for modern scientific programming thanks to its rich ecosystem of libraries (NumPy, SciPy, Pandas). Ideal for prototyping and data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;r&#34;&gt;R&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specialized language for statistical computing and data visualization. Widely used in biology, medicine, and social sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;julia&#34;&gt;Julia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A young language that combines the speed of C with the convenience of Python. Gaining popularity in computational math and machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;matlab&#34;&gt;MATLAB&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industry standard in engineering computation and signal processing. Features powerful built-in tools for matrix operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;key-features&#34;&gt;Key Features&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;performance&#34;&gt;Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimization for numerical computation is a critical requirement for scientific languages. Many of them use JIT compilation or interfaces with low-level languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;specialized-libraries&#34;&gt;Specialized libraries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Availability of packages for specific areas: bioinformatics, quantum chemistry, computer vision, and other highly specialized tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-visualization&#34;&gt;Data Visualization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built-in or easily pluggable tools for graphical presentation of results are a must for scientific languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;current-trends&#34;&gt;Current trends&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The convergence of scientific programming languages is blurring the boundaries between them. Today, researchers often combine several tools, using, for example, Python for data preprocessing and Julia for computationally intensive calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;language-selection&#34;&gt;Language selection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is universal, R is ideal for statistics, MATLAB dominates engineering, and Julia offers a revolutionary approach to performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-direction&#34;&gt;Future direction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Development is moving towards simplifying interactions between languages, creating unified data standards, and automating routine operations in the research cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The post for the week of May 19-25</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;start-of-the-week&#34;&gt;Start of the week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The week began with intense preparation for a discrete math quiz. It was pretty straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-game-release&#34;&gt;First game release&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first version of the game has been finished, I&amp;rsquo;ve uploaded it to the Yandex games site. It turned out pretty good, but there is room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;language-learning&#34;&gt;Language learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further I continue to learn German, it is much harder than English. I am trying to develop my vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;finally-got-out-of-the-house&#34;&gt;Finally got out of the house&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the weekend I had a chance to meet some friends I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen for a long time. We discussed a lot of things, it was quite fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TypeScript and its advantages</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/summary10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/summary10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TypeScript is no longer just a trendy tool - it&amp;rsquo;s a necessity for professional web development. Here are the top reasons to switch to TypeScript:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reliability-and-predictability&#34;&gt;Reliability and predictability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TypeScript&amp;rsquo;s static typing catches errors before the code runs. No more surprises like “undefined is not a function” in production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;improved-development-experience&#34;&gt;Improved development experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smart hints and autocompletion in the IDE work much better thanks to the type system. You spend less time reading documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-scalability&#34;&gt;Better scalability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TypeScript is ideal for large projects and teamwork. The type system serves as a living documentation and simplifies code maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;smooth-migration&#34;&gt;Smooth migration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t have to rewrite your entire project at once. You can gradually add types to existing JavaScript code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;state-of-the-art-features&#34;&gt;State-of-the-art features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TypeScript includes all the latest JavaScript features plus additional features like interfaces, generics, and decorators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;community-support&#34;&gt;Community Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TypeScript is supported by Microsoft and is heavily used in Angular, Vue 3, React, and other popular frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switching to TypeScript is an investment in the quality of your code and your professional development. You may start gradually, but the result is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
